Guide to the Maritime History Collection PR 100
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
- Series II. Medium Format Flat Files
  - Subseries II.3: Naval Vessles
    - A (Box Flat File, Folder FF 21)
      This file contains photographs of the U.S.S. Alliance, U.S.S. America, U.S.S. Amphitrite, U.S.S. Annapolis and U.S.S. Arionza.
    - B (Box Flat File, Folder FF 22)
      This file contains photographs of the U.S.S. Brooklyn, U.S.S. Boston, U.S.S. Cruiser Birmingham, U.S.S. Cruiser Baltimore, and a print of the U.S.S. Bonhome Richard.
    - C (Box Flat File, Folder FF 23)
      This file contains clippings from periodicals, photographs and Nathaniel Currier's lithograph U.S. Frigate Cumberland.
    - USS Constitution (Box Flat File, Folder FF 24)
    - D-G (Box Flat File, Folder FF 25)
      This file contains photographs and the lithograph Launch of the Steam Frigate Fulton the First, at New York 29th, Octr. 1814.
    - H-I (Box Flat File, Folder FF 26)
      This file contains clippings from periodicals and photographs.
    - J-L (Box Flat File, Folder FF 27)
      This file contains photographs, clippings from periodicals and prints.
    - M (Box Flat File, Folder FF 28)
      This file contains clippings from periodicals, photographs (including a gelatin silver print by James Grabow of the Mothball Fleet on the Hudson River) and the lithographs U.S. Steam Frigate Mississippi Passing Punta Tristao and U.S. Practice Ship 'Marion' Capt. S.B. Luce.
    - USS Maine (Box Flat File, Folder FF 29)
    - N (Box Flat File, Folder FF 30)
      This file contains photographs and clippings from periodicals.
    - USS New York (Box Flat File, Folder FF 31)
      This file contains clippings from periodicals, photographs and the Currier & Ives lithograph Armoured Steel Cruiser New York, United States Navy.
    - O (Box Flat File, Folder FF 32)
      This file contains clippings from periodicals, photographs and the Nathaniel Currier lithograph U.S. Ship of the Line Ohio
    - P (Box Flat File, Folder FF 33)
      This file contains photographs, the engraving La Fregate des Etats-unis d'Amerique, le President, venant d'appareiller, avec des ris dans les Huniers and the lithograph U.S. Ship Pennsylvania. Charles Stewart Esq. Comr.
    - R-S (Box Flat File, Folder FF 34)
      This file contains photographs and the lithograph Die Amerikanische Kriegsfregatte St. Lawrence
    - T-Z (Box Flat File, Folder FF 35)
      This file contains clippings from periodicals, photographs and the lithograph U.S. Steam Frigate Wabash. In a gale on the night of the 29th of Nov.r 1856, off Cape Hatteras.
    - Submarines (Box Flat File, Folder FF 36)
    - Naval Vessels- Foreign (Box Flat File, Folder FF 37)
      This file contains clippings from periodicals, photographs and H.M. Currie & Son's lithograph H.M.S. Shannon.
    - British Naval Ships- HMS Ramillies (Box Flat File, Folder FF 38)
      This file contains three prints after paintings by Robert Dodd.
    - Multiple Ships (Box Flat File, Folder FF 39)
    - Unidentified Ships (Box Flat File, Folder FF 40)
      This file contains clippings from periodicals, photographs and Nathaniel Currier's lithograph U.S. Ship of the Line in a Gale.
  - Subseries II.4: Ship Details
    - Ship Details- Miscellaneous (Box Flat File, Folder FF 41)
      This file contains clippings from The Navy and Army Illustrated and The Illustrated London News.
  - Subseries II.5: Views
    - Miscellaneous (Box Flat File, Folder FF 42)
      This file contains clippings from periodicals and photographs of Howe Caverns and the U.S. Maritime Service Training Station in Sheepshead Bay, Brooklyn.
    - United States (Box Flat File, Folder FF 43)
      This file contains lithographs and engravings of the U.S. Naval Asylum,the Burning of Savannah and Virginia.
    - Annapolis, United States Naval Academy (Box Flat File, Folder FF 44)
      This file contains photographs of the US Naval Academy.
    - Annapolis, United States Naval Academy (Box Flat File, Folder FF 45)
      Separated Materials note
    - Foreign (Box Flat File, Folder FF 46)
      This file contains prints of foreign views, including John Boydell's engravings of Woolwich and Greenwich Hospital.
    - Monuments and Memorials (Box Flat File, Folder FF 47)
      This file contains clippings from periodicals and prints.
    - Ship Yards and Dry Docks (Box Flat File, Folder FF 48)
  - Subseries II.6: Clippings, Papers & Ephemera
    - The Evolution of a Leviathan: How the Steamship Developed (Box Flat File, Folder FF 49)
      This file contains clippings from The London Illustrated News.
    - Theatrical Productions (Box Flat File, Folder FF 50)
      This file contains clippings from The Sphere, The Sketch and The London Illustrated News.
    - USS Maine (Box Flat File, Folder FF 51)
  - Subseries II.7: Events
    - Naval Battles
      - Thrid Anglo-Dutch War (Box Flat File, Folder FF 52)
      - Third Anglo-Dutch War (Box Flat File, Folder FF 53)
      - Seven Years War (Box Flat File, Folder FF 54)
        This file contains engravings for Harrison's edition of Rapin's History of England.
      - Revolutionary War (Box Flat File, Folder FF 55)
        This file contains clippings from periodicals and prints, including an engraving by J. Boydell of the engagement between the Serapis and Bonhomme Richard.
      - Barbary War (Box Flat File, Folder FF 56)
        This file contains several prints picturing naval engagements and events from the Barbary war, including an engraving of The Blowing Up of the Fire Ship Intrepid.
      - War of 1812- Miscellaneous (Box Flat File, Folder FF 57)
        This file contains several prints picturing naval engagements from the War of 1812, including lithographs by Samuel Walters and an engraving of the Peacock and L'Epervier after Thomas Birch.
      - War of 1812- Battle of Lake Champlain (Box Flat File, Folder FF 58)
        This file contains several prints, including Benjamin Tanner's engraving and Nathaniel Currier's lithograph of Macdonough's Victory on Lake Champlain.
      - War of 1812- Battle of Lake Erie (Box Flat File, Folder FF 59)
        This file contains clippings from periodicals and several prints, including Nathaniel Currier's Perry's Victory on lake Erie and Naval Heros of the United States.
      - War of 1812- USS Chesapeake & HMS Shannon (Box Flat File, Folder FF 60)
        This file contains several prints, including Boarding and Taking the American Ship Chesapeake.
      - War of 1812- USS Constitution & the Guerriere (Box Flat File, Folder FF 61)
        This file contains clippings from periodicals and prints, including Brilliant Naval Victory, after S. Seymour, Strickland and Kneass' engraving Signal Naval Victory and Nathaniel Currier's lithograph The Constitution and Guerriere.
      - USS Constitution & the Java (Box Flat File, Folder FF 62)
        This file contains clippings from periodicals and prints, including R. and D. Havell's The Java in a Sinking State and D.W. Kellogg's The Capture of H.B.M.'s Sloop of War Java by the U.S. Frigate Constitution.
      - War of 1812- USS United States & British Frigate Macedonian (Box Flat File, Folder FF 63)
        This file contains prints, including S. Seymour's Capture of H.B.M. Friagate Macedonian.
      - War of 1812- USS Wasp & HMS Frolic (Box Flat File, Folder FF 64)
        This file includes clippings from periodicals and prints, including F. Kearny's and S. Seymour's engravings of the capture of the H.B.M. Sloop of War Frolic.
      - War of 1812- Images depicting multiple battles (Box Flat File, Folder FF 65)
        This file contains clippings from periodicals and prints, including Packard & Van Benthuysen's American Naval Victories.
      - Civil War- Miscellaneous (Box Flat File, Folder FF 66)
        This file contains clippings from periodicals and prints, including Currier & Ives' The Great Naval Victory in Mobile Bay and The U.S. Sloop of War "Kearsage" 7 Guns, Sinking the Pirate "Alabama" 8 Guns.
      - Civil War- Battle between the Monitor & the Merrimac (Box Flat File, Folder FF 67)
        This file contains several prints, including lithographs by Currier & Ives and Endicott & Co.
      - Spanish American War- Miscellaneous (Box Flat File, Folder FF 68)
        This file contains clippings from periodicals and several prints.
      - Spanish American War- Destruction of the USS Maine (Box Flat File, Folder FF 69)
        This file contains photographs, clippings from periodicals and several prints.
      - Unidentified Battles (Box Flat File, Folder FF 70)
    - Events - Miscellaneous
      - Dewey Naval Parade (Box Flat File, Folder FF 71)
        This file contains Pach Brother's photographs of the 1899 Dewey Naval Parade.
      - Fisher's Island Sham Battle (Box Flat File, Folder FF 72)
        This file contains clippings from periodicals and photographs of the 1891 Fisher's Island sham battle.
      - Races (Box Flat File, Folder FF 73)
        This file contains clippings from periodicals, prints and lithographs.
      - Shipwrecks & Fires - Photographs (Box Flat File, Folder FF 74)
      - Shipwrecks & Fires - Prints (Box Flat File, Folder FF 74a)
  - Subseries II.8: Model Ships
    - Miscellaneous (Box Flat File, Folder FF 75)
  - Subseries II.9: Portraits
    - A-D (Box Flat File, Folder FF 76)
      This file contains clippings from periodicals and prints, including a portrait of Stephen Decatur engraved by Asher B. Durand after a painting by Thomas Sully.
    - F-H (Box Flat File, Folder FF 77)
      This file contains clippings from periodicals, prints and photographs, including a Pach Brother's portrait of Rear Admiral Caspar F. Goodrich. This file also contains portraits of Albert Gallatin, Alexander Hamilton ,Admiral David Glasgow Farragut, President U.S. Grant and Susan Parker Hayes.
    - John Paul Jones (Box Flat File, Folder FF 78)
      This file contains original prints and photographic reproductions of portraits of John Paul Jones.
    - L-R (Box Flat File, Folder FF 79)
      This file contains clippings from periodicals and prints, including several portraits of Commodore Matthew Perry.
    - S-Z (Box Flat File, Folder FF 80)
    - Group Portraits - Prints (Box Flat File, Folder FF 81)
    - Group Portraits - Photographs (Box Flat File, Folder FF 82)
- Series III. Large Format Flat Files
  Series III, Large Format Flat Files, includes material between 24 x 40 and 30 x 40 inches. Materials are arranged by type of ship.
  - Subseries III.1: Sailing Vessels
    - Miscellaneous (Box Flat File, Folder FF 83)
      This file contains advertisements and several lithographs, including Currier & Ives prints of the yachts Gracie of and Jeannette.
  - Subseries III.2: Steamships
    - A (Box Flat File, Folder FF 84)
      This file contains prints of various steamships, including the the U.S. Mail Steam Ships Atlantic and Artic, the Alida, the Astoria of New York, the British & North American Royal Mail Steamship Asia, the Alaska, the steamer America and others.
    - B (Box Flat File, Folder FF 85)
      This file contains photographs and prints of the steamships Britannia, Britannic, Bristol, Baltic, Bremen and others.
    - Ca-Ch (Box Flat File, Folder FF 86)
      This file contains photographs and prints of the China, the Steam Ferry Boat Central. the C.H. Northam, the Caledonia and others.
    - Ci (Box Flat File, Folder FF 87)
      This file includes photographs and prints of the steamships City of Peking, City of Tokio, City of Worcester, City of Columbus, City of New York, City of Boston and others.
    - Cl-Cz (Box Flat File, Folder FF 88)
      This file contains prints of the steamships Clermont, Columbus, Conte Di Savoia, Columbia, Clyde, Concordia and Continental.
    - D (Box Flat File, Folder FF 89)
      This file contains prints of the steamships Dixie, Dean Richmond, Drew, De Grasse and Duca D'Aosta,
    - E (Box Flat File, Folder FF 90)
      This file contains prints of the steamships Empire State, Empress of Russia, Etruria, Empress of Asia, Empire of Troy, Elm City, Empire City, and Elbe.
    - F (Box Flat File, Folder FF 91)
      This file contains prints of the steamships Francis Skiddy, Frostburg and Furnessia.
    - G-I (Box Flat File, Folder FF 92)
      This file contains prints of the steamships Great Eastern, Great Western, Gate City, Great Republic, General Grant, Granite State, S.S. Independence, Holsatia, Habana and La Savoie.
    - J-L (Box Flat File, Folder FF 93)
      This file contains prints of the steamships Lafayette, John Brooks, Jersey City, James W. Baldwin and Iroquois.
    - M (Box Flat File, Folder FF 94)
      This file includes prints of the steamships Montreal, Media, Majestic, Mary Powell, Manhattan and Massachusetts.
    - N-O (Box Flat File, Folder FF 95)
      This file contains prints of the steamships New world, Ne-Shan-Nock, New York, Old Dominion and Oregon.
    - P-R (Box Flat File, Folder FF 96)
      This file contains prints of the steamships Pacific, Plymouth Rock, Ponce, Presidente Wilson, Priscilla, R.M.S. Queen Elizabeth, Rex, Rotterdam and Rhode Island.
    - Queen Mary (Box Flat File, Folder FF 97)
    - S (Box Flat File, Folder FF 98)
      This file contains images of the steamships St. John, State of New York, Saratoga, Sirius, Spain, St. Laurent, Scythia and others.
    - T-V (Box Flat File, Folder FF 99)
      This file contains prints of the steamships United States, Trojan, Tunisian, Victorian and Thomas Powell.
    - W (Box Flat File, Folder FF 100)
      This file contains prints of the steamships Washington Irving and Werra.
    - Unidentified (Box Flat File, Folder FF 101)
    - Interiors (Box Flat File, Folder FF 102)
      This file contains a photograph of a steamship interior.
  - Subseries III.3: Naval Vessels
    - A-Z (Box Flat File, Folder FF 103)
      This file contains images of the U.S. Steam Gun Boat Kanawah, U.S. Sloop of War Richmond, U.S. Frigate Constitution, U.S. Frigate Savannah, U.S. Sloop of War Jamestown, U.S. Ship of War Delaware, U.S. Frigate St. Lawrence, U.S.S. Enterprise, U.S. Ship North Carolina, the Metropolis of Beverly, U.S.S. Ohio, U.S. Gun Boat Ashuelot and the Elco PT.
    - USS Maine (Box Flat File, Folder FF 104)
      This file contains clippings from periodicals, prints and photographs picturing the U.S.S. Maine.
    - Ironclads (Box Flat FIle, Folder FF 105)
      This file contains images of the steamer "Keokuk", U.S. Monitor "Weehawken, U.S. Steam Sloop "Iroquois", U.S. Steam Frigate Roanoke, U.S. Iron Clad Ram "Dictator", U.S. Iron Clad Screw Ram "Dunderberg" and U.S. Iron Clad Steamer "New Ironsides".
    - Multiple Ships (Box Flat File, Folder FF 106)
      This file contains images of the New York, Marblehead, Boston and Bennington.
    - Foreign & Unidentified Ships (Box Flat File, Folder FF 107)
  - Subseries III.4: Other Ships
    - Ferries (Box Flat File, Folder FF 108)
      This file contains photographs and lithographs, including Currier & Ives print New York Ferry Boat.
    - Tugboats (Box Flat File, Folder FF 109)
      This file contains photographs and prints.
    - Plans and Drawings- Miscellaneous (Box Flat Files, Folder FF 110)
      This file contains a plan of the U.S.S. Monitor, the Barque California, the Clermont, U.S. Frigate Chesapeake and others.
    - Plans & Drawings- Dredge boats (Box Flat File, Folder FF 111)
      This file contains plans of dredge boats, including the U.S. Dredge Boat Essayons.
    - Plans & Drawings - Yachts - by Saunders & West Co. (Box Flat File, Folder FF 112)
      This file contains original plans for yachts designed by Saunders & West Co., including Mr. Starbuck's steam yacht Tillie.
  - Subseries III.5: Views
    - Miscellaneous (Box Flat File, Folder FF 113)
      This file contains photographs, including a photo of the launching of the U.S. Battleship California at Brooklyn Naval Yard on April 28, 1904.
  - Subseries III.6: Clippings & Ephemera
    - Miscellaneous - Newspaper Clippings (Box Flat File, Folder FF 114)
      This file contains various newspaper clippings, including a 1921 article from the Boston Evening Transcript that details the history and collections of the Naval History Society.
    - Miscellaneous - Ephemera (Box Flat File, Folder FF 115)
      This file contains ephemera, including advertisements for steamships and prints.
  - Subseries III.7: Events
    - Naval Battles
      - War of 1812-Miscellaneous (Box Flat File, Folder FF 116)
        This file contains battle scenes of the War of 1812, including Macdonough's Victory on Lake Champlain, Capture of H.B.M. Sloop of War Frolic by the U.S> Sloop of War Wasp, engravings after battle scenes painted by Thomas Birch and others.
      - War of 1812- Miscellaneous (Box Flat File, Folder FF 116a)
        This file is not accesible due to condition issues. It contains This Representation of the U.S. Frigate Constitution, Isaac Hull, Esq. Commander, Capturing His Britannic Majesty's Frigate Guerriere, James R. Dacres,Esq.Commander, an engraving after a painting by Thomas Birch. Another copy of this engraving can be found in flat file 116, War of 1812- Miscellaneous.
      - War of 1812- Miscellaneous (Box Flat File, Folder FF 116b)
        This file is not accessible due to condition issues. It contains United States and Macedonian, an engraving after a painting by Thomas Birch. Another copy of this engraving can be found in flat file 116, War of 1812- Miscellaneous.
      - War of 1812- Battle of Lake Erie (Box Flat File, Folder FF 117)
        his file contains the engravings Perry's Victory on Lake Erie, after J.J. Barralet, Perry's Victory on Lake Erie, after Thomas Birch and others.
      - War of 1812- Battle of Lake Erie (Box Flat File, Folder FF 118)
        This file contains the engravings Perry's Victory on Lake Erie, after J.J. Barralet, Perry's Victory on Lake Erie, after Thomas Birch and This representation of the Battle on Lake Erie is respectfully inscribed to Commodore Perry his Officers and gallant Crews By their humble servant, James Webster.
      - War of 1812- Battle of Lake Erie (Box Flat File, Folder FF 118a)
        This file is not accessible due to condition issues. It contains the print This representation of the Battle on Lake Erie is respectfully inscribed to Commodore Perry his Officers and gallant Crews By their humble servant, James Webster. Another copy of this print can be found in FF 118.
      - War of 1812- USS Chesapeake & HMS Shannon (Box Flat File, Folder FF 119)
        This file contains several prints of the Battle of the USS Chesapeake and HMS Shannon, including a set of lithographs published by Smith, Elder & Co with an accompanying key.
      - War of 1812- USS Constitution & the Java (Box Flat File, Folder FF 120)
        This file contains prints of the battle between the USS Constitution and HMS Java, including a set of four engravings after paintings by Nicholas Pocock.
      - Civil War-Miscellaneous (Box Flat File, Folder FF 121)
        This file contains prints picturing various naval battles of the Civl War, including the bombardment of forts Hatteras and Clark and others.
      - Civil War- Battle between the Monitor & the Merrimac (Box Flat File, Folder FF 122)
        This file contains prints picturing the battle between the Monitor and Merrimac.
      - Civil War- Battle between the Monitor & the Merrimac (Box Flat File, Folder 122a)
        This file is not accessible due to condition issue. It contains the lithograph Desperate Encounter Between the Ericsson Battery "Monitor" 2 Guns, And The "Merrimac", 12 Guns.
      - Civil War- Battle of Port Royal (Box Flat File, Folder FF 123)
        This file contains prints picturing the Battle of Port Royal.
      - Spanish American War- Miscellaneous (Box Flat File, Folder 124)
        This file contains prints picturing naval battles of the Spanish American War, including Bombardment of Matanzas.
      - Spanish American War- Destruction of the USS Maine (Box Flat File, Folder FF 125)
        This file contains prints picturing the destruction of the USS Maine.
      - Miscellaneous Naval Battles (Box Flat File, Folder FF 126)
        This file contains prints picturing miscellaneous naval battles from the eighteenth through the early twentieth centuries.
    - Miscellaneous
      - British Naval Expeditions (Box Flat File, Folder FF 127)
        This file contains prints picturing British naval expeditions, including images of the Battle of Havana (1782) and the Napoleonic Wars.
      - Naval Reception for Li Hung Chang (Box Flat File, Folder FF 128)
        This file contains photographs of the naval reception for the Chinese diplomat Li Hung Chang in New York harbor on August 28, 1896.
      - Races (Box Flat File, Folder FF 129)
        This file contains photographs and prints of various races, including Currier & Ives lithograph Vigilant and Valkyrie in a "Thrash to Windward".
  - Subseries III.8: Portraits
    - A-Z (Box Flat File, Folder 130)
      This file contains newspaper clippings and prints of various naval personalities, including Commodore John Paul Jones, Rear-Admiral D.G. Farragut and Admiral George Dewey among others.
- Series IV: Oversize Flat files
  Series IV, Oversize Flat Files, includes material larger than 30 x 40 inches. Material is arranged by ship type. The majority of images in this series depict steamboats.
  - Subseires IV.1: Sailing Vessels
    - Ceres, circa 1800 (Oversize Flat file, Folder FF131)
    - Yachts (Oversize Flat file, Folder FF 132)
  - Subseries IV.2: Steamships
    - A (Oversize Flat file, Folder FF 133)
    - B (Oversize Flat file, Folder 134)
    - C (Oversize Oversize, Folder FF135)
    - City of ______ (Oversize Flat file, Folder FF 136)
    - D-E (Oversize Flat file, Folder 137)
    - F-G (Oversize Flat file, Folder FF 138)
    - H (Oversize Flat file, Folder FF 139)
    - K (Oversize Flat file, Folder FF 140)
    - L (Oversize Flat file, Folder FF 141)
    - M (Oversize Flat file, Folder FF 142)
    - N (Oversize Flat file, Folder FF 143)
    - P (Oversize Flat file, Folder FF 144)
    - R (Oversize Flat file, Folder FF 145)
    - S (Oversize Flat file, Folder FF 146)
    - T (Oversize Flat file, Folder FF 147)
    - White Star Line (includes Oceana, Queen Elizabeth and Queen Mary) (Oversize Flat file, Folder FF 148)
    - Unidentified (Oversize Flat file, Folder FF 149)
  - Subseries IV.3: Naval Vessels
    - USS Chesepeke, USS Constitution, Ironclad Keokuk (Oversize Flat file, Folder FF 150)
  - Subseries IV.4: Advertising posters
    - Private Signals of the Merchants of Boston (Oversize Flat file, Folder FF 151)
    - Development of Shipping (Hamburg-American Line) (Oversize Flat file, Folder FF 151)